<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Toasty Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://tylerhmorgan.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tylerhmorgan.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-12T19:10:43-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://tylerhmorgan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tyler Morgan(toasty_nerd)]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[toasty@filesynergy.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome]]></title>
    <link href="http://tylerhmorgan.com/blog/2014/02/12/welcome/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-12T18:48:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tylerhmorgan.com/blog/2014/02/12/welcome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is another attempt to start a blog about my personal take on web development. I can&rsquo;t count how many blogs
I&rsquo;ve started before this but they always seem to pitter out before they really get going. I can&rsquo;t promise that
I will continue to update this blog from now until the end of time but I can say that I&rsquo;ll try to keep it
going for at least a few weeks. I already have some ideas for posts that mostly revolve around Ruby and
Ruby on Rails but before I get into that it&rsquo;s probably time for me to introduce myself.</p>

<p>My name is Tyler Morgan, I go by toasty, toastynerd or toastycrack on different corners of the internet
as befitting my needs. I have been tinkering with computers and technology since I was in middle school,
it included a little bit of code but nothing beyond simple games and shells scipts. I just recently decided to try
to make a living out of writing code. My chosen platform&mdash;or the platform that was chosen for me&mdash;is Ruby
and Ruby on Rails and most of this blog will reflect that.</p>

<p>I currently am a developer at an early stage startup. It&rsquo;s early enough that I can&rsquo;t give too many details
but it&rsquo;s called Makindo and focuses on social media and data analytics. Most of my blog posts are going to
come directly from issues I&rsquo;ve had to tackle while working for Makindo. Much of the information is going
be available elsewhere on the internet. I&rsquo;ll try to link to pages and posts that I&rsquo;ve found especially
useful and maybe I&rsquo;ll throw in an affiliate link to Amazon if I really like a book. Hopefully, it won&rsquo;t be
too obtrusive. That&rsquo;s the plan but as they say, details fucking suck. Oh yeah, heads up, I like to curse.</p>

<p>-Toasty</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
